<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">

<topic id="topic17" xml:lang="en">
  <title id="kk171433">Backing Up Databases with Data Domain Boost</title>
  <body>
    <p>EMC Data Domain Boost (DD Boost) is EMC software that can be used with the
        <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> and <codeph>gpdbrestore</codeph> utilities to perform faster
      backups to the EMC Data Domain storage appliance. Data Domain performs deduplication on the
      data it stores, so after the initial backup operation, the appliance stores only pointers to
      data that is unchanged. This reduces the size of backups on disk. When DD Boost is used with
        <codeph>gpchrondump</codeph>, Greenplum Database participates in the deduplication process,
      reducing the volume of data sent over the network. When you restore files from the Data Domain
      system with Data Domain Boost, some files are copied to the master local disk and are restored
      from there, and others are restored directly.</p>
    <p>With Data Domain Boost managed file replication, you can replicate Greenplum Database backup
      images that are stored on a Data Domain system for disaster recover purposes. The
        <codeph>gpmfr</codeph> utility manages the Greenplum Database backup sets that are on the
      primary and a remote Data Domain system. For information about <codeph>gpmfr</codeph>, see the
        <i>Greenplum Database Utility Guide</i>.</p>
    <p>Managed file replication requires network configuration when a replication network is being
      used between two Data Domain systems:</p>
    <ul>
      <li id="kk178323">The Greenplum Database system requires the Data Domain login credentials to
        be configured using <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph>. Credentials must be created for both the
        local and remote Data Domain systems. </li>
      <li id="kk178334">When the non-management network interface is used for replication on the
        Data Domain systems, static routes must be configured on the systems to pass the replication
        data traffic to the correct interfaces.</li>
    </ul>
    <p>Do not use Data Domain Boost with <codeph>pg_dump</codeph> or <codeph>pg_dumpall</codeph>. </p>
    <p>Refer to Data Domain Boost documentation for detailed information.</p>
    <note type="important">For incremental back up sets, a full backup and the associated
      incremental backups must be on a single device. For example, a backup set must all be on a
      file system. The backup set cannot have some backups on the local file system and others on a
      Data Domain system. </note>
    <note>You can use a Data Domain server as an NFS file system (without Data Domain Boost) to
      perform incremental backups. </note>
  </body>
  <topic id="topic18" xml:lang="en">
    <title>Data Domain Boost Requirements</title>
    <body>
      <p>Using Data Domain Boost requires the following.</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Data Domain Boost in included only with Pivotal Greenplum Database. </li>
        <li id="kk169399">Purchase and install EMC Data Domain Boost and Replicator licenses on the
          Data Domain systems.</li>
        <li id="kk169390">Obtain sizing recommendations for Data Domain Boost. Make sure the Data
          Domain system supports sufficient write and read streams for the number of segment hosts
          in your Greenplum cluster.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>Contact your EMC Data Domain account representative for assistance.</p>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic19" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="kk161655">One-Time Data Domain Boost Credential Setup</title>
    <body>
      <p>There is a one-time process to set up credentials to use Data Domain Boost. Credential
        setup connects one Greenplum Database instance to one Data Domain instance. If you are using
        the <codeph>gpcrondump --replicate</codeph> option or Data Domain Boost managed file
        replication capabilities for disaster recovery purposes, you must set up credentials for
        both the local and remote Data Domain systems. </p>
      <p>To set up credentials, run <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> with the following options:</p>
      <codeblock>--ddboost-host <varname>ddboost_hostname</varname> --ddboost-user <varname>ddboost_user</varname> 
--ddboost-backupdir <varname>backup_directory</varname></codeblock>
      <p>To remove credentials, run <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> with the
          <codeph>--ddboost-config-remove</codeph> option.</p>
      <p>To manage credentials for the remote Data Domain system that is used for backup
        replication, include the <codeph>--ddboost-remote</codeph> option with the other
          <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> options. For example, the following options set up credentials
        for a Data Domain system that is used for backup replication. The system IP address is
          <codeph>192.0.2.230</codeph>, the user ID is <codeph>ddboostmyuser</codeph>, and the
        location for the backups on the system is <codeph>GPDB/gp_production</codeph>:</p>
      <codeblock>--ddboost-host 192.0.2.230 --ddboost-user ddboostmyuser 
--ddboost-backupdir gp_production --ddboost-remote</codeblock>
      <p>For details, see <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> in the <i>Greenplum Database Utility
        Guide</i>.</p>
      <p>If you use two or more network connections to connect to the Data Domain system, use
          <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> to set up the login credentials for the Data Domain hostnames
        associated with the network interfaces. To perform this setup for two network connections,
        run <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> with the following options:</p>
      <codeblock>--ddboost-host <varname>ddboost_hostname1</varname> 
--ddboost-host <varname>ddboost_hostname2</varname> --ddboost-user <varname>ddboost_user</varname> 
--ddboost-backupdir <varname>backup_directory</varname></codeblock>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic20" xml:lang="en">
    <title>Configuring Data Domain Boost for Greenplum Database</title>
    <body>
      <p>After you set up credentials for Data Domain Boost on the Greenplum Database, perform the
        following tasks in Data Domain to allow Data Domain Boost to work with Greenplum
        Database:</p>
      <ul>
        <li id="kk164115">
          <xref href="#topic21" type="topic" format="dita"/>
        </li>
        <li id="kk164176">
          <xref href="#topic20b" type="topic" format="dita"/>
        </li>
        <li id="kk171548">
          <xref href="#topic23" type="topic" format="dita"/>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic21" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="title21">Configuring Distributed Segment Processing in Data Domain</title>
    <body>
      <p>Configure the distributed segment processing option on the Data Domain system. The
        configuration applies to all the DCA servers and the Data Domain Boost plug-in installed on
        them. This option is enabled by default, but verify that it is enabled before using Data
        Domain Boost backups: </p>
      <codeblock># ddboost option show</codeblock>
      <p>To enable or disable distributed segment processing:</p>
      <codeblock># ddboost option set distributed-segment-processing {enabled | disabled}</codeblock>
    </body>
    <topic id="topic20b">
      <title id="topic20b">Configuring Advanced Load Balancing and Link Failover in Data
        Domain</title>
      <body>
        <p>If you have multiple network connections on a network subnet, you can create an interface
          group to provide load balancing and higher network throughput on your Data Domain system.
          When a Data Domain system on an interface group receives data from the media server
          clients, the data transfer is load balanced and distributed as separate jobs on the
          private network. You can achieve optimal throughput with multiple 1 GbE connections. </p>
        <note type="note">To ensure that interface groups function properly, use interface groups
          only when using multiple network connections on the same networking subnet.</note>
        <p>To create an interface group on the Data Domain system, create interfaces with the
            <codeph>net</codeph> command. If interfaces do not already exist, add the interfaces to
          the group, and register the Data Domain system with the backup application. </p>
        <ol id="ol_wxj_lxw_yq">
          <li id="kk163338">Add the interfaces to the
              group:<codeblock># ddboost ifgroup add interface 192.0.2.1
# ddboost ifgroup add interface 192.0.2.2
# ddboost ifgroup add interface 192.0.2.3
# ddboost ifgroup add interface 192.0.2.4
</codeblock><note
              type="note">You can create only one interface group and this group cannot be
              named.</note></li>
          <li id="kk163346">Select one interface on the Data Domain system to register with the
            backup application. Create a failover aggregated interface and register that interface
            with the backup application.<note type="note">You do not have to register one of the
                <codeph>ifgroup</codeph> interfaces with the backup application. You can use an
              interface that is not part of the <codeph>ifgroup</codeph> to register with the backup
              application.</note></li>
          <li id="kk163367">Enable <codeph>ddboost</codeph> on the Data Domain
            system:<codeblock># ddboost ifgroup enable</codeblock></li>
          <li id="kk163369">Verify the Data Domain system configuration as
              follows:<codeblock># ddboost ifgroup show config</codeblock><p>Results similar to the
              following are
              displayed.<codeblock>Interface
-------------
192.0.2.1
192.0.2.2
192.0.2.3
192.0.2.4
-------------
</codeblock></p></li>
        </ol>
        <p>You can add or delete interfaces from the group at any time.</p>
        <note type="note">Manage Advanced Load Balancing and Link Failover (an interface group)
          using the <codeph>ddboost ifgroup</codeph> command or from the <menucascade>
            <uicontrol>Enterprise Manager Data Management</uicontrol>
            <uicontrol>DD Boost</uicontrol>
          </menucascade> view.</note>
      </body>
    </topic>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic23" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="kk166437">Export the Data Domain Path to the DCA Network</title>
    <body>
      <p>The commands and options in this topic apply to DDOS 5.0.x and 5.1.x. See the Data Domain
        documentation for details.</p>
      <p> Use the following Data Domain commands to export the <codeph>/backup/ost</codeph>
        directory to the DCA for Data Domain Boost backups.
          <codeblock># nfs add /backup/ost 192.0.2.0/24, 198.51.100.0/24 (insecure)</codeblock><note
          type="note">The IP addresses refer to the Greenplum system working with the Data Domain
          Boost system.</note></p>
    </body>
    <topic id="topic24" xml:lang="en">
      <title>
        <ph>Create the Data Domain Login Credentials for the DCA</ph>
      </title>
      <body>
        <p> Create a username and password for the DCA to access the DD Boost Storage Unit (SU) at
          the time of backup and restore: </p>
        <codeblock># user add <varname>user</varname> [password <varname>password</varname>] [priv {admin | security | user}]</codeblock>
      </body>
    </topic>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic25" xml:lang="en">
    <title>Backup Options for Data Domain Boost</title>
    <body>
      <p>Specify the <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> options to match the setup. </p>
      <p>Data Domain Boost backs up files to the Data Domain system. Status and report files remain
        on the local disk. </p>
      <p>To configure Data Domain Boost to remove old backup directories before starting a backup
        operation, specify a <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> backup expiration option:</p>
      <ul>
        <li id="kk169801">The <codeph>-c</codeph> option clears all backup directories.</li>
        <li id="kk169821">The <codeph>-o</codeph> option clears the oldest backup directory.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>To remove the oldest dump directory, specify <codeph>gpcrondump --ddboost</codeph> with the
          <codeph>-o</codeph> option. For example, if your retention period is 30 days, use
          <codeph>gpcrondump --ddboost</codeph> with the <codeph>-o</codeph> option on day 31.</p>
      <p>Use <codeph>gpcrondump --ddboost</codeph> with the <codeph>-c</codeph> option to clear out
        all the old dump directories in <codeph>db_dumps</codeph>. The <codeph>-c</codeph> option
        deletes all dump directories that are at least one day old.</p>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <concept id="concept_urz_chb_br">
    <title>Using CRON to Schedule a Data Domain Boost Backup</title>
    <conbody>
      <section>
        <ol id="ol_vpv_bdb_br">
          <li id="kk160664">Ensure the <xref href="#topic19" type="topic" format="dita"/> is
            complete.</li>
          <li id="kk159968">Add the option <codeph>--ddboost</codeph> to the
              <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> option:<p>
              <codeblock>gpcrondump -x mydatabase -z -v --ddboost </codeblock>
            </p></li>
        </ol>
        <note type="important">Do not use compression with Data Domain Boost backups. The
            <codeph>-z</codeph> option turns backup compression off.<p>Some of the options available
            in <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> have different implications when using Data Domain Boost.
            For details, see <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> in the <i>Greenplum Database Utility
              Reference</i>.</p></note>
      </section>
    </conbody>
  </concept>
  <topic id="id_gj5_zwq_rt">
    <title>Restoring From a Data Domain System with Data Domain Boost</title>
    <body>
      <ol id="ol_ljx_mlv_ft">
        <li id="kk167029">Ensure the <xref href="backup-ddboost.xml#topic19"/> is complete.</li>
        <li id="kk167030">Add the option <codeph>--ddboost</codeph> to the
            <codeph>gpdbrestore</codeph>
          command:<codeblock>$ gpdbrestore -t <i>backup_timestamp</i> -v -ddboost</codeblock></li>
      </ol>
      <note type="note">Some of the <codeph>gpdbrestore</codeph> options available have different
        implications when using Data Domain. For details, see <codeph>gpdbrestore</codeph> in the
          <i>Greenplum Database Utility Reference</i>.</note>
    </body>
  </topic>
</topic>
