<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_z4g_32q_54">
  <title>Using LDAP Authentication with TLS/SSL </title>
  <shortdesc>You can control access to Greenplum Database with an LDAP server and,
    optionally, secure the connection with encryption by adding parameters to
      <filepath>pg_hba.conf</filepath> file entries.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>Greenplum Database supports LDAP authentication with the TLS/SSL protocol to
      encrypt communication with an LDAP server: <ul id="ul_eyn_1gq_54">
        <li>LDAP authentication with STARTTLS and TLS protocol &#8211; STARTTLS starts with a clear
          text connection (no encryption) and upgrades it to a secure connection (with
          encryption).</li>
        <li>LDAP authentication with a secure connection and TLS/SSL (LDAPS) &#8211; Greenplum Database uses the TLS or SSL protocol based on the protocol that is used
          by the LDAP server. </li>
      </ul></p>
    <p>If no protocol is specified, Greenplum Database communicates with the LDAP
      server with a clear text connection.</p>
    <p>To use LDAP authentication, the Greenplum Database master host must be
      configured as an LDAP client. See your LDAP documentation for information about configuring
      LDAP clients.</p>
    <section>
      <title>Enabing LDAP Authentication with STARTTLS and TLS</title>
      <p>To enable STARTTLS with the TLS protocol, specify the <codeph>ldaptls</codeph> parameter
        with the value 1. The default port is 389. In this example, the authentication method
        parameters include the <codeph>ldaptls</codeph> parameter.
        <codeblock>ldap ldapserver=myldap.com ldaptls=1 ldapprefix="uid=" ldapsuffix=",ou=People,dc=pivotal,dc=com"</codeblock></p>
      <p>Specify a non-default port, with the <codeph>ldapport</codeph> parameter. In this example,
        the authentication method includes the <codeph>ldaptls</codeph> parameter and the and
          <codeph>ldapport</codeph> parameter to specify the port
        550.<codeblock>ldap ldapserver=myldap.com ldaptls=1 ldapport=500 ldapprefix="uid=" ldapsuffix=",ou=People,dc=pivotal,dc=com"</codeblock></p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Enabing LDAP Authentication with a Secure Connection and TLS/SSL </title>
      <p>To enable a secure connection with TLS/SSL, add <codeph>ldaps://</codeph> as the prefix to
        the LDAP server name specified in the <codeph>ldapserver</codeph> parameter. The default
        port is 636.</p>
      <p>This example <codeph>ldapserver</codeph> parameter specifies a secure connection and the
        TLS/SSL protocol for the LDAP server <codeph>myldap.com</codeph>.</p>
      <codeblock>ldapserver=ldaps://myldap.com</codeblock>
      <p>To specify a non-default port, add a colon (:) and the port number after the LDAP server
        name. This example <codeph>ldapserver</codeph> parameter includes the
          <codeph>ldaps://</codeph> prefix and the non-default port 550.</p>
      <codeblock>ldapserver=ldaps://myldap.com:550</codeblock>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Notes</title>
      <p>Greenplum Database logs an error if the following are specified in an
          <filepath>pg_hba.conf</filepath> file entry: <ul id="ul_cws_m3q_54">
          <li>If both the <codeph>ldaps://</codeph> prefix and the <codeph>ldaptls=1</codeph>
            parameter are specified.</li>
          <li>If both the <codeph>ldaps://</codeph> prefix and the <codeph>ldapport</codeph>
            parameter are specified.</li>
        </ul></p>
      <p>Enabling encrypted communication for LDAP authentication only encrypts the communication
        between Greenplum Database and the LDAP server. </p>
      <p>See <xref href="client_auth.xml#topic5" format="dita"/> for information
        about encrypting client connections. </p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Examples</title>
      <p>These are example entries from an <filepath>pg_hba.conf</filepath> file.</p>
      <p>This example specifies LDAP authentication with no encryption between Greenplum Database and the LDAP server. </p>
      <codeblock>host all plainuser 0.0.0.0/0 ldap ldapserver=myldap.com ldapprefix="uid=" ldapsuffix=",ou=People,dc=pivotal,dc=com"</codeblock>
      <p>This example specifies LDAP authentication with the STARTTLS and TLS protocol between
          Greenplum Database and the LDAP server. </p>
      <codeblock>host all tlsuser 0.0.0.0/0 ldap ldapserver=myldap.com ldaptls=1 ldapprefix="uid=" ldapsuffix=",ou=People,dc=pivotal,dc=com" </codeblock>
      <p>This example specifies LDAP authentication with a secure connection and TLS/SSL protocol
        between Greenplum Database and the LDAP server. </p>
      <codeblock>host all ldapsuser 0.0.0.0/0 ldap ldapserver=ldaps://myldap.com ldapprefix="uid=" ldapsuffix=",ou=People,dc=pivotal,dc=com"</codeblock>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
